<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Anno quarto Henrici octaui. These be the statutes established in diuers Parlyaments, for the mistery of the pewterers of London and concerning the search of pewter, brasse, and vntrue beames and weights, and for deceiuable hawkers, with diuers other orders and redresses to be had in the sayd mystery, with the renewing and confirming of the same statutes,</title>
            <title>Public General Acts. Selections: Pewterers.</title>
            <author>England and Wales.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1593</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 36 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 12 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A06312</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 16783</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S107729</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99843425</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99843425</idno>
            <idno type="VID">8157</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A06312)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 8157)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 476:08)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Anno quarto Henrici octaui. These be the statutes established in diuers Parlyaments, for the mistery of the pewterers of London and concerning the search of pewter, brasse, and vntrue beames and weights, and for deceiuable hawkers, with diuers other orders and redresses to be had in the sayd mystery, with the renewing and confirming of the same statutes,</title>
                  <title>Public General Acts. Selections: Pewterers.</title>
                  <author>England and Wales.</author>
                  <author>Wood, Thomas, fl. 1593.</author>
                  <author>Mayor, William.</author>
                  <author>Hyll, Walter.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[24] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[At London printed :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Anno Domini. 1593]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Imprint from colophon.</note>
                  <note>Signed: Thomas Wood Maister. William Mayor Walter Hyll Wardens.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-C⁴.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Worshipful Company of Pewterers of London --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:8157:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:8157:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>ANNO QVARTO <hi>Henrici octaui.</hi>
            </p>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>royal coat of arms</figDesc>
               <q>HONI SOIT QVI MALO Y PENSE</q>
            </figure>
            <p>Theſe be the Statutes eſtabli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed in diuers Parlyaments, for the miſtery of the Pewterers of Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don, and concerning the ſearch of pew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, braſſe, and vntrue beames and weights, and for deceiuable Hawkers, with diuers other orders and redreſſes to be had in the ſayd myſtery, with the renewing and confirming of the ſame Statutes,</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="Act">
            <pb facs="tcp:8157:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:8157:2"/>
            <head>¶ An acte made the fourth yeere of our Soueraigne Lord, King Henry the viij. concerning Pewterers, and true weights and Beames. the vij. chapter.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>OR as much as a certaine Acte was made and ſtabliſhed, in the Parlyament holden at Weſtmin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, the xix. of the raigne of the laſt moſt famous King, your Father, Henry the vij. (whom GOD pardon:) concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning Pewterers and Braſiers, hawking and walking about the Countryes, and alſo concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning falſe Beames, Scales and Weights, with a prouiſion for caſting of fine Mettall and of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect goodneſſe, which acte was made to endure to the next Parliament, the tennor whereof inſueth.</p>
            <p>That where many ſimple and euill diſpoſed perſons, of thys your Realme of England, vſing the ſayd crafts, daily go about this your Realme, from village, from Towne, and from houſe to houſe, aſwel in woods and Forreſts, as other pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, to buy Pewter and Braſſe. And that know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing theeues and other pickers, that ſteale aſwell Pewter and Braſſe belonging to your High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and vnder your marke, and to the Lordes ſpirituall and temporall, as to other your Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iectes of thys your Realme, bring ſoch ſtolen veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels to them, in ſuch hid places to ſell, and ſell it for little or nought, and about they bring it to pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uie places, or into corners of Citties or Townes,
<pb facs="tcp:8157:3"/>and there ſel much part of it to ſtraungers, which carry it ouer the Sea by ſtealth.</p>
            <p>Alſo, the ſayde perſons ſo going about, and diuers other vſing the ſayde craftes, vſe to make newe veſſels, and to mixt good mettall and bad togethers, and make it nought and ſell it for good ſtuffe: where in deede the ſtuffe and mettall thereof, is not worth the fourth part that it is ſolde for, to the great hurt, deceyt and loſſe of your Subiects.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Nota.</label> Alſo, dyuers perſons vſing the ſayde crafts, haue deceiueable and falſe Beames and Scales,
that one of them wyll ſtand euen with twelue pound weight at the one ende, againſt a quarter of a pounde at the other ende, to the ſinguler ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uantage of themſelues, and to the great deceyt and loſſe of your Subiects, buyers and ſellers with them.</p>
            <p>
               <label>The ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naunce.</label> For reformation of the premiſes, it woulde pleaſe your Highueſſe,
of your moſt aboundaunt grace, with the aduiſe of your Lordes ſpirituall and temporall, and the commons in this preſent Parlyament aſſembled, and by the authoritie of the ſame, to enact and ſtabliſh, that no perſon, nor perſons, vſing the ſayde craft of Pewterers and Braſiers, from henceforth ſhall ſell or chaunge any Pewter or braſſe, newe or olde, at any place, or places, within this your Realme; but onely in open Fayers or Markets, or in theyr own dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling houſes, but if they be deſired by the the buy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers of ſuch wares: vppon paine of forfeiture to our Soueraigne Lorde the King,
<note place="margin">Penalttie x. pound.</note> for euery ſuch Default, ten pounds.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:8157:3"/>
            <p>
               <label>Nota.</label> Alſo by the ſame authority, may it be eſtabli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed, that no perſon, nor perſons, of what con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition or degree ſo euer, hee or they bee, from henceforth (wythin the Cittie of London, and Yorke, or without,) eyther caſt, or worke any Pewter veſſels, or Braſſe, at any place, or pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, within this your Realm: but that it be as good fine mettall, as is the Pewter and braſſe, caſt and wrought after the perfect goodneſſe of the ſame within the Cittie of London, and by the ſtatutes of the ſame ought to be, vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> payne of forfeiture of all ſuch Pewter and Braſſe ſo caſt and wrought, of worſe Pewter or Braſſe than ought to be wrought in the ſame Citties. The one halfe of euery ſuch forfeiture, to bee to the vſe of your Highneſſe, and the other halfe to the vſe of the finders therof.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Prouiſion</label> Prouided alwayes, that thys forfeyture in no wiſe extend to braſſe or pewter, being in the poſſeſſion of any perſon, other than the wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers of the ſame, or ſuch as haue the ſame to ſell, and beeing of the craftes or miſtery. <label>Nota.</label> Alſo that it may by the ſame authoritie be enacted and ſtabliſhed, that no maner of perſon, or per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, of what degree or condition ſoeuer, hee or they be, fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hence forth make no hollowe wares of Pewter. That is to ſay, Saltes and Pots, that is made of pewter, called ley mettall, but that it may bee after the aſſyſe of pewter ley mettall wrought within the Cittie of London.
<label>Penaltie.</label> And that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> makers of ſuch wares, ſhall marke the ſame with ſeuerall markes of theyr owne, to the intent that the makers of ſuch wares
<pb facs="tcp:8157:4"/>ſhall auowe the ſame wares by them (as is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boueſayd) to bee wrought.</p>
            <p>And that all and euery ſuch wares, not ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiently made and wrought, and not marked in fourme aboue ſaide, founden in the poſſeſſion of the ſame maker or ſeller, to bee forfeited. <label>Penaltie.</label> And if the ſame ware be ſold, the ſaide maker to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feit y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> value of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame, ſo vnlawefully wrought and ſold, the one halfe of the ſaide wares, or the value thereof, to be to the vſe of your Higneſſe, and the other half to be to the vſe of the finders or ſearchers of the ſame.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Beams &amp; weights.</note> Alſo that it may (by the ſame authoritie) be enacted and ſtabliſhed, that if any perſon or perſons, heereafter vſing buying and ſelling of Pewter or braſſe, that hereafter occupy and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaueable or falſe beames, or weights, of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſaid wares, that euery ſuch perſon or perſons vſing or occupying ſuch deceiuable &amp; vntrue beames or weights, to forfeit twentie ſhillings: the one halfe to the King, and the other halfe to the party that therefore ſhall ſue by action of debt. And that in the ſayde action, no protection nor eſſoyne ſhall bee allowed. And alſo the ſayde party ſo offending, ſhall forteit hys Beame to him that ſhall ſeaſe it. And if the ſaide offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, or offenders, be not ſufficient to pay y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſayd ſomme, or ſommes, by them ſo forfeited, that then it ſhall be lawful to the Mayors, Baylifs, or other head Officers of ſuch place, or places, where any ſuch offenders ſhalbe found, to put them in the Stockes, and them ſo to keepe till the next Market day, next adioyning, and in
<pb facs="tcp:8157:4"/>the Market place to put them in the Pillory all the Market time. And furthermore, that it be lawfull by the ſayd authoritie,
<note place="margin">Search.</note> that the Mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter and Wardaines of the ſayd craft of Pew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terers, within euery Cittie or Borough of this Realme, where ſuch wardaines are. And where no ſuch wardaines are, the head officers or gouernours of the ſame Cittie, or Borough, to appoint certaine perſons moſt expert in the knowledge of the ſame to make ſearch wythin the ſaid Citties or boroughs where they dwel. And ouer this, the Iuſtices of peace wythin e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery ſhire, at the generall Seſſyons holden at Michaelmas, ſhall aſſigne and appoynt two certayne perſons, hauing experience therin, to make ſearch in the premiſes, in euery part of the ſhire, as wel within the franchiſe as with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out, ſauing in Citties or boroughs where ſear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers be appointed by the heads or gouernours of the ſame. And that all ſuch vnlawfull pew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter or braſſe, as the ſayde ſearchers ſhall finde, the one halfe to the vſe of your Grace, and the other halfe to the ſearchers. And that in the default of the ſayde Maiſters and Mardaines of the ſaide occupations, not ſearching in forme as is aforeſaid, and whereby that any ſuch vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawfull Mettall is caſt or made, or vnlawfull weightes vſed, that then it ſhalbe lawful to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny perſon, or perſons, hauing ſuffici<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>et cunning &amp; knowledge in the ſaide occupations, by ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſight of the Maiors, Baylifs, or head Officers of the ſaid Citties, and boroughs, and townes, to ſearch all the ſaide places, and to put thoſe
<pb facs="tcp:8157:5"/>ſaide authoritie and acte in execution, in forme aforeſaide. Pleaſe it therefore your Grace, and wiſdomes, in ſo much as the ſaid act is thought good and profitable, that it bee ordayned, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>acted, and eſtabliſhed, by the Lordes ſpirituall and temporall, and the commons in this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Parlyament aſſembled, and by the autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie of the ſame, that the ſaide acte may endure for euer.
<note place="margin">For true mettall<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ct work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manſhip.</note> And ouer, that it bee enacted by the ſaid authority, that if any vntrue, or deceiuable mettall, or workmanſhip of Tinne or Pewter, bee founden, eyther in Platters, Chargers, Diſhes, Sawcers, Potengers, Trenchers, Baſons, Flagons, Bottles, Pottes, Saltſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers, Goblers, Spoones, Cruets, or Candle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtickes, or in any other ſuch wares of Tinne or Pewter, where ſoeuer it bee caſt, made, or wrought, within this Realme or without, and brought to bee ſolde wythin the ſame Realme. That then it ſhall bee lawfull to the Mayor of the Cittie of London, and the Mayſter and Wardaynes of the craft of Pewterers of the ſayd Cittie, for the time being, and theyr depu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyes, to haue ſearch of the ſame, within the cit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of London, and the ſuburbes of the ſame, and that in all other Citties, Boroughs, and Townes, where any Mardaines be, or ſhal be, the Mayors, Baylifs, or head Officers, and Mardaines to haue like authoritie.</p>
            <p>And where no Mardaynes be, then the head Officers or gouernours of the ſame Citties, Boroughs, and Townes, to appoint certaine perſons moſt expert &amp; cunning in knowledge
<pb facs="tcp:8157:5"/>of the ſame, to make ſearch within y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſayd citties, Boroughs, and Townes where they dwell.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Pewter being de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectiue to be forfei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted.</note> And if any ſuch new wares, wrought of Tin and Pewter as is aforeſayd, be found defectiue, and being in the poſſeſſion of the ſeller, that then the ſame perſon or perſons, that putteth any ſuch new wares of pewter to ſale, ſhal forfeit the ſame wares, the one half to the vſe of our Soueraigne Lord the King, and the other halfe to the ſearch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers or finders of the ſame.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Prouiſion</label> Prouided alway, that this act concerning y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feiture, be not preiudiciall or hurtfull to any perſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> or perſons, hauing graunt of our Soueraigne Lord y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> King, or of any of his noble Progenitors by his letters pattents of ſuch forfeiture, but that they and euery of them ſhal haue &amp; enioy the ſame according to their former graunts and liberties.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="Act">
            <head>An Acte concerning Pewterers, made in the xxv. yeere of the reigne of our So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueraigne Lord, King Henry the eyght, in the minth Chapter.</head>
            <p>
               <label>Peticion.</label> 
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N theyr moſt lamentable wiſe ſhow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en,
and pitteouſly complaine vnto the Kings moſt royall Maieſtie, &amp; to this moſt high Courte of Parliament, the Kings moſt humble poore and obeyſaunt ſubiects, the Maiſter, wardaines, &amp; poore fellowſhip of the craft &amp; miſtery of Pewterers, as wel of the Citty of London, as of all other places within thys Realme of England, that where the ſaid craft or
<pb facs="tcp:8157:6"/>miſtery, before this time hath been one of the beſt handicrafts within this Realme, which hath not onely growen and contiuued by meane of diuers good acts and ſtatutes made for the true exerciſe of the ſame, whereof one was made in the xir. yeere of the Kings moſt renowmed Father, whoſe ſoule God pardon. And one other was made in the fourth yeere of the Kings moſt victe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious raign, concerning the crafts of Pewterers and Braſiers, of &amp; for the true making, mixting and ſelling of good and true pewter, and braſen veſſels. And alſo for exerciſing and vſing of true weights and beames, to be occupyed by the ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers of any ſuch pewter or braſen veſſels, within thys Realme, ſo that none of the Kings Subiects, nor any other perſon, ſhould (by any ſale of any falſe mixed braſen and pewter veſſell, or any vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>true weights) bee deceiued, as by the ſayde ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutes more plainely dooth appeare.</p>
            <p>Which good Statutes duely put in execution, hath cauſed the ſaide craft to encreaſe and mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiplye, to the great profite and vtilitie of a great number of the Kings Subiects, and the commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditie of pewter veſſell much to be had in reputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, in all ſtraunge Regions and Countreys, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till now of late, diuers euill diſpoſed perſons, bee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Kings Subiects borne, which haue been apprentiſes and brought vp, in the exerciſe of the ſayde crafte of Pewterers, haue nowe of late, for their ſingular lucre, repayred into ſtraunge Regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and Countreys, and there doo exerciſe the ſaide craft of Pewterers, teaching ſtraungers
<pb facs="tcp:8157:6"/>(not onely the cunning of mixting and forging of all manner of Pewter veſſell) but alſo doo teach all thinges belonging to the ſayde craft of Pew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terers. By meanes whereof, there is not onely brought (daylie into this Realme) out of ſtrange Regions to bee ſolde, great number of thinges made of Pewter, vntruely mixted, and made of Tinne, where with the Kings Subectes bee dai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>he deceiued, and the people of ſtrange Countries greatly inſtructed, in the cunning of the ſaid craft of Pewterers, in ſuch wiſe that thereby not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly a great number and quantity of pewter veſſel, and other things of pewter, made in diuers ſorts and faſhions, amounting to a great value, which was dayly and continually wont to bee carryed and conueied out of this Realme, by Merchants, into ſtraunge Regions and Countries, and there to be ſold and vended. Whereby the commoditie of Tin made into Pewter veſſell, which hath bin had in great eſtimation, as things very neceſſary and commodious, &amp; the kings cuſtomes thereby much aduaunced, is nowe lyke vtterly to ceaſe and decay, and not to bee eſteemed as heere to fore hath beene but alſo the ſayde craft of Pewterers, which at this day ſetteth and keepeth in worke and occupation, a great number of people, ſhalbe be vtterly vndone. And a great multitude of the Kings natural ſubiects, thereby fall into idlenes, to the great impoueriſhment of this Realme, if ſpeedy remedy for the redreſſe of the premiſes bee not prouided.</p>
            <p>In tender conſideration wherof, and for refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation
<pb facs="tcp:8157:7"/>of the premiſſes,
<note place="margin">Any man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of Pewter wrought out of this Realm to be forfei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted.</note> it may pleaſe your high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, by the aſſent of the Lords ſpirituall and temporal, and the commons in this preſent Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyament aſſembled, and by the authoritie of the ſame, to ordayne and enact, that no perſon or per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons hereafter, at any time now inhabiting, or which hereafter ſhal inhabite within this Realm ſhall buy, or otherwiſe take by exchaung for other wares, any wares made, or hereafter to be made out of this Realme,
<note place="margin">Search &amp; ſeaſure.</note> of Tin, or mixt with Tin, as Platters, Diſhes, Sawcers, Pottes, Baſyns, Ewers, Flagons, Goblets, Salte, Saltſellers, Spoones, or any other thing made of Tinne or Pewter as aforeſaide, whatſoeuer it bee, vppon paine of forfeiture of the ſame ware, in whoſe hands ſoeuer it may be found or taken: and alſo, lawfull money currant in this Realme to the va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lue thereof. The one halfe of the ſame forfeiture to be to the vſe of the Kings Highneſſe, and the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther halfe to the vſe of the finders of the ſame.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Penaltie.</label> And furthermore be it enacted, that it ſhall bee lawfull for the Maiſter &amp; wardaines of the ſayde craft of Pewterers, as well within the Cittie of London, as within euery other Citty, Borough, and Town of this Realm where ſuch wardaines bee. And where no ſuch wardaynes bee, to the head Officer or gouernour, head Officers or go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernours of the ſame Cittie, Borough, or towne, for the time beeing, to appoynt diuers perſons moſt expert in knowledge of the ſame, to make ſearch and ſeaſure, and to take into theyr hands and poſſeſſion all ſuch wares as heereafter ſhall be brought contrary to the true intent and effect
<pb facs="tcp:8157:7"/>of thys preſent Acte, in whoſe ſoeuer handes or poſſeſſions any ſuch ſhall be found.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Prentiſes or Iour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney-men ſtrau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gers borne.</note> And alſo be it enacted by the authoritie aboue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaide, that no perſon or perſons, occupying the ſayde craft or occupation of Pewterers, wythin this Realme, ſhall ſet on worke, or retayne in hys or theyr ſeruice, any perſon or perſons, to be his or their Apprentice or Iourney-man, beeing ſtraun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger borne out of this Realme, vppon payne to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feit for euery ſuch Apprentice and Iourney-man, ten poundes ſterling. <note place="margin">Strau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gers ſhall not worke pewter within the Realme.</note> And that no ſtraunger, borne out of this Realm, ſhall occupy, exerciſe, or vſe from the feaſt of Penticoſt, next comming, the ſaide craft of Pewterers, nor worke any manner of veſſell or other ware aforeſaide to bee made of Tinne or Pewter, within any place or places of this Realme, vppon payne of forfeiture of tenne pounds ſterling: and alſo, vppon payne of forfei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of the ſame Pewter or Tinne ſo wrought, in whoſe hands ſoeuer it may be taken or found.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Exerciſe beyond Sea.</note> And alſo, bee it enacted by authoritie aforeſaid, that no perſon nor perſons, beeing borne within this Realme, occupying or excerciſing the ſayde craft of Pewterers, ſhall at any time heere alter reſort to any ſtraunge Regions or Countreyes, there to vſe, teach or exerciſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſaid craft of Pew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terers, vpon paine to looſe the priueledge and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefite of an Engliſhman. And if in caſe any of the Kings Subiects at this preſent time, beeing dwelling in any ſtraunge Countrey or Region, and there occupying the ſayde craft of Pewte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, doo not repayre into thys Realme, within three moneths next after requeſt and warning
<pb facs="tcp:8157:8"/>to him be giuen, by writing ſealed with the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon ſeale of the Wardaynes of the ſayde craft, within the ſayde Cittie of London, and heere in this Realme continually from henceforth dwel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> inhabit, that then &amp; from henceforth he ſhalbe ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken &amp; reputed as no Engliſhman, but ſhall ſtand &amp; be from henceforth out of the Kings protection.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Hawkers.</note> And foraſmuch as ſundry euil diſpoſed perſons which commonly bee called Hawkers, by autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie of the Kings letters pattents or placarde, do not only goe about from place to place, within this Realme, vſing buying and ſelling of braſſe and pewter. And by coulour and pretence of the ſame Lycenſes and Placardes, vſe vnlawfull and deceyueable Weights and Beames, but alſo do vſe to ſell both pewter and braſſe, which is not good, nor truely, nor lawfully mixt nor wrought, to the great deceit of the Kings true liege people, contrary to the fourme and effect of the ſayd good Act and Statute made in the ſayde fourth yeere of the Kings moſt noble raigne. Be it therefore enacted by authority of this preſent Parliament, that all ſuch lycences and placardes heeretofore had, made, or graunted to any ſuch perſon or per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, contrarie to the true meaning, fourme, and effect of thys Statute ſhalbe from hencefoorth by authoritie of this preſent Parliament, cleerely voyde and of none effect. And where as in the ſaide acte of Parliament, (concerning the craft of Pewterers &amp; Braſiers) made in the ſayde fourth yeere, for diuers cauſes and conſiderations in the ſame contayned, among other things, it is expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed that no perſon, or perſons, vſing the ſaid craft
<pb facs="tcp:8157:8"/>of Pewterers or Braſiers ſhould fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> henceforth fill or chaunge any Pewter or braſſe, new or olde, at any place or places within this Realme, but onely in open Fayres and Markets, or in theyr stone dwelling houſes, but if they were deſired by the buyers of ſuch wares, vpon paine of forfei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture for euery ſuch default, ten pounds.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Hawkers.</label> For as much as the ſame forfeiture is to the only vſe of the Kings highneſſe, &amp; that any partie ſearching or finding the ſame, is not intituled to haue any benefit therby, it hath not been knowen that any perſon, or perſons, haue taken any paine to inſearch or make any inquiry thereof. By rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon whereof, diuers and many euill diſpoſed per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, vſing buying and ſelling both of braſſe and pewter, and not regarding the ſaide good act, nor the ſaid penalty, daily goe about from village to village, Towne &amp; towne, and from houſe to houſe, to ſell ſuch pewter and braſſe, which is not good. And alſo vſe deceiueable Weyghts and Beames as they did before the making of the ſayd acte, to the great hurt and deceite of the Kings true liege people and Subiects.
<note place="margin">Penalty for Haw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers.</note> Wherefore be it enacted by the authoritie aboueſayde, that as well the moytie of the ſayd forfeiture of ten poundes, limi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in the ſaide eſtatute made in the ſayd fourth yeere, as alſo the moytie of all other forfeitures before expreſſed, and euery of them bee and ſhall bee to the vſe of the Kings highneſſe, his Heyres and Succeſſors: and the other moytie of the ſame forfeitures, and euery of them, to the vſe of him, or them, that ſhall ſeaze, finde, or preſent the ſayd forfeitures, or any of them, or that ſhall ſue for
<pb facs="tcp:8157:9"/>the ſame in any competent Court or Courtes, within this Realme by action of debt, bill, plaint or information, wherein the defendant ſhall in no wiſe be admitted to wage his law, or any protec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion or eſſoyne to any perſon or perſons, which ſhalbe impeached to haue offended contrary to the forme and effect of this Statute, ſhall be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowable. This acte to endure to the laſt day of the next Parliament.</p>
            <div type="annotation">
               <head>
                  <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> The annotations of the confirmacions and renouations of the aforeſayde Statutes.</head>
               <p>
                  <label>Confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation.</label> ANd it is to be noted that the ſaide laſt act was reuewed in the Parliament holden at Weſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minſter, the viij. day of Iune, in the xxviii. yeere of our ſayde Soueraigne Lorde, to and among other actes. And that all cauſes, articles, &amp; pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſions therein contayned, to ſtand in their force and ſtrength, to the laſt day of the next Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. And alſo, the ſayde acte was renewed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gayne in the Parlyament holden at Weſtminſter the xviij. of Aprill, in the xxj. yeere of our ſayde Soueraigne Lorde, amongſt other actes, as is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foreſayde. &amp;c.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="Act">
            <head>An acte concerning Pewterers made in the xxxiij. yeare of the raigne of our Soueraigne Lord King Henry the viij. Chap. iiij.</head>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Recitall of the Statute made the xxx. yere</note> WHere at the Parlyament begun at London the third day of Nouember,
in the xxj. yeere
<pb facs="tcp:8157:9"/>of the raigne of the King our Soueraigne Lord, and from thence adiourned to Weſtminſter, and there holden, and from that time continued by diuers progenitors, vnto the xv. day of Ianuary, the xxv. yeere of his moſt noble raigne, it was or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dayned and eſtabliſhed by the aſſent of the Kings Maieſty, his Lords ſpiritual &amp; temporal, and the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mons in the ſaid Parlyament then aſſembled, and by the authoritie of the ſame, that no perſon, or perſons, from that time than inhabiting, or which after that time ſhould inhabit within this Realm, ſhould buy, or otherwiſe take by exchange for other wares, any manner wares made, or heereafter to be made out of this Realme, of Tin, or mixt with Tin, as Platters, Diſhes, ſawcers, Pots, Baſins, Ewers, Flagons, Goblettes, Saltes, Saltſellers, Spoones, or any other thing made of Tin or pewter as aforeſayd, what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer it were, vppon payne of forfeiture of the ſame wares, in whoſe hands ſoeuer it might bee found or taken, and alſo lawfull money currant in this Realme, to the full value thereof, the one halfe of the ſame forfeiture to be to the vſe of the Kings highneſſe, and the other halfe to be to the vſe of the finders of the ſame. And further it was enacted, that it ſhould be lawfull to the Maiſter and Wardaines of the Pewterers, as wel with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the Cittie of London, as within euery other Cittie, Borough, or Towne within this Realme where ſuch Wardaines were, and where no ſuch Wardaynes were, to the head Officer or gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, head Officers or gouernours of the ſame Cittie, Borough, or Towne for the time beeing,
<pb facs="tcp:8157:10"/>to appoint diuers perſons, moſt expert in know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of the ſame, to make ſearch and ſeaſure and to take into their hands and poſſeſſeſſion, all ſuch wares as thereafter ſhould be brought, contrarie to the true intent and effect of the ſayde act, in whoſe ſoeuer hands or poſſeſſions any ſuch hold be found. And it was alſo enacted by the authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie aboue ſayde, that no perſon, or perſons, occu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pying the ſayde craft or occupation of Pewte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers, within thys Realme, ſhould ſet on worke, or retaine in his or theyr ſeruice, any perſon, or per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, to be his or their apprentice, or Iourneyman eſtraunger borne out of this Realme, vpon paine to forfeyt for euery ſuch Apprentice and Iourney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, ten poundes ſterling: And that no ſtraun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, borne out of this Realme, ſhould occupy, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe, or vſe, from the feaſt of Penticoſt then next comming, the ſaid craft of Pewterers, nor worke any manner of veſſels, nor other ware aforeſayd, to be made of Tin or Pewter, within any place or places of this Realme, vpon paine of forfeiture of ten poundes ſterling: and alſo, vppon payne of forfeiture of the ſame pewter or Tin, ſo wrought, in whoſe handes ſoeuer it ſhould be found or ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken. And it was further enacted by the ſayde au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie, that no perſon, or perſons, beeing borne within this Realme, then occupying or exerciſing the ſayd craft of Pewterers, ſhould from thence<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forth reſort into any ſtraunge Regions or Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treys, there to vſe, teach, or exerciſe the ſaide craft of Pewterers, vpon paine to looſe the Priueledge and benefite of an Engliſhman.</p>
            <p>And if in caſe any of the Kings Subiects, at
<pb facs="tcp:8157:10"/>that time being, dwelling in any ſtraunge Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey or Region, and there occupying the ſaid craft of Pewterers, dyd not repayre into this Realme, within three moneths next after requeſt &amp; war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning to him to be giuen, by writing ſealed wyth the common ſeale of the Wardaines of the ſayde craft, within the ſaid Cittie of London, and here in this Realme continually (from thencefoorth) dwel and inhabit, that then and from henceforth he ſhould bee reputed and taken as no Engliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, but ſhould ſtand and be from henceforth out of the Kings protection.</p>
            <p>And it was than further enacted, that where ſundry euill diſpoſed perſons, which commonly were called hawkers, by authority of the Kings Letters patents, or Placarde, did not onely goe about from place to place, within this Realme, v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing buying and ſelling of braſſe and pewter, and by collour and pretence of the ſame Lycenſes or Placardes, did not only vſe vnlawfull &amp; deceiue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able weights and beames, but alſo did vſe to ſell both Braſſe and Pewter which was not good, nor truely or lawfully mixt or wrought, to the great deceit of the Kings true liege people, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the fourme and effect of a good and lau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dable acte and ſtatute, made in the fourth yeere of the Kings ſaid moſt noble raigne, that all ſuch lycences &amp; placards, afore that time had made or graunted to any ſuch perſon, or perſons, contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie to the true meaning, fourme, and effect of the ſayd eſtatute, ſhould bee from thencefoorth by the authority of the ſayd Parliament, cleerely voyde and of none effect. And where as in the ſayde
<pb facs="tcp:8157:11"/>acte of Parliament (concerning the ſayd craft of Pewterers &amp; Braſiers) made in the ſaide fourth yeere, for diuers cauſes and conſiderations in the ſame act contained, amongſt other things, it was expreſſed, that no perſon or perſons, vſing the ſaid craft of Pewterrrs or Braſiers, ſhould from henceforth ſell or chaunge any pewter or Braſſe, newe or olde, at any place or places within thys Realme, but onely in open Faires and Markets, or in their owne dwelling houſes, but if they were deſired by the buyers of ſuch wares, vpon paine of forfeiture for euery ſuch defaulte tenne poundes. And ſo than the ſame forfeiture was to the onely vſe of the Kings highnes, and the party ſearching or finding the ſame was not intituled to haue any benefite therby: it was not knowen that any perſon or perſons had taken any paines to inſearch or make any inquiry thereof. By rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon wherof diuers &amp; many euill diſpoſed perſons than vſing buying and ſelling as wel of braſſe as pewter, and not regarding the ſaid good acte, nor the ſaide penalty, went dayly about from Village to Village, Towne to Towne, and from houſe to houſe, to ſell ſuch pewter and braſſe, which was not good, and alſo vſed deceiueable weights and Beames, as they did before the making of the ſayd acte, to the great hurt and deceit of the kings true liege people and Subiectes. Wherefore it was enacted by the authoritie of the ſayde Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, that aſwell the moytie of the ſayd forfey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of ten poundes lymited in the ſaide ſtatute made in the ſaide fourth yeere, as alſo the moytie of all other forfeitures and penalties, expreſſed
<pb facs="tcp:8157:11"/>and ſpecified in the ſayd actes, and euery of them ſhould be to the vſe of the Kings Highneſſe, hys Heyres and Succeſſors, and the other moytie of the ſame forfeitures and penalties, and euery of them, to the vſe of him or them that would feaze, finde, or preſent the ſame forfeitures, or any of them, or that would ſue for the ſame in any com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petent Court or Courtes within this Realme, by action of debt, byll, plaint or information where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the defendant ſhould in no wiſe bee admitted to wage his lawe, or any protection or eſſoyne to any perſon or perſons which ſhould be impeach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to haue offended, contrary to the forme and ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect of this Statute, ſhould bee allowable, as in the ſayde acte more plainly appeareth, which acte was appointed to endure onelie to the ende of the next Parliament, then next following, &amp; which act was afterward renewed in the Parliament holden at Weſtminſter, in the xxviij. yeere of the raigne of our ſaid Soueraigne Lord, to endure vntill the ende of the next Parliament then next following: And which act was alſo renewed at the Parliament holden at Weſtminſter, in the xxxj. and xxxii. yeeres of our ſayde Soueraigne Lordes raigne to endure vntill the laſt day of the next Parlyament then next enſuing:
<label>Confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation.</label> Prayen therefore in this preſent Parliament our ſayde Soueraigne Lords true and obedient Subiects, the Pewterers of this his ſaide Realme, &amp; other the true commons of the ſame, becauſe the ſame acte is beneficiall and neceſſary for the common-wealth of this Realme: That it may be enacted by the Kinge our ſayde Soueraigne Lorde, the
<pb facs="tcp:8157:12"/>Lordes ſpirituall &amp; temporall, and the commons in the preſent Parliament aſſembled, and by au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie of the ſame, for as much as the ſame act, and euery thing therin contained, is good and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neficiall to the Common-wealth of this Realme, that all and euery the ſayde actes and ſtatutes, and all &amp; euery article, ſentence, and clauſe com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſed in the ſame, may from henceforth ſtand and abide in as full ſtrength and effect, for euermore from henceforth to endure, according to the pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port, tenour and effect of the ſame act and actes, as though the ſayd articles, ſentences, and clauſes, were ſpecially lymited, recited, or declared in this preſent act. <note place="margin">Wares made &amp; brought from be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond the Sea.</note> And that no perſon, ne perſons, from hencefoorth buy or take by exchaunge, or other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe take into or within this Realme, to the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent to ſell any ſuch thinges or wares, aboue re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hearſed, made or to be made out of this Realme, vpon paine of like forfeitures &amp; penalties, as are and were expreſſed in the ſayde ſeuerall acts, the ſame penaltyes and forfeitures to be leuyed as is afore expreſſed.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Maiſter and War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daines ſhall not be let to ſearch.</note> And that it may be further enacted by authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie aforeſaide, that if any perſon, or perſons, doo vnlawfully withſtand, interrupt, diſturbe, or let the Maiſter and Wardaines, or their deputies of the ſayd craft of Pewterers, for the time beeing, or the head Officer or gouernour, head Officers or gouernours of Citties, Townes, &amp; Boroughs, within this Realm, wherin no ſuch Maiſter and Wardaines are, or ſhalbe, or any of them, in ſear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching, ſeaſing, and taking into their handes and poſſeſſions ſuch wares as ſhall happen to bee
<pb facs="tcp:8157:12"/>bought, or brought into thys Realme contrary to the purport and effect of the ſayde eſtatute, made in the ſayde xxv. yeere of the raigne of our ſayde Soueraigne Lorde, that then euery ſuch perſon, and perſons, ſo offending, in letting, diſturbing, or withſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding the ſayd ſeaſure, or taking of ſuch wares as is aforeſaide, ſhall looſe and forfeit for euery time ſo dooing, the ſumme of fyue poundes ſterling, the one halfe wherof, ſhalbe to the Kings vſe, and the other halfe to him or them that will or ſhall ſue for the ſame, by action of debt, writ, byll, playnt, or information in any the Kings Courtes of recorde, in which action or ſuite, no Protection, Priuiledge, nor wager of law, ſhall be allowed nor admitted.</p>
            <closer>God ſaue the Queene.
<signed>
                  <list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Thomas Wood</hi> Maiſter.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>William Mayor</hi> Wardens.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Walter Hyll.</hi> Wardens.</item>
                  </list>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>
               <hi>AT LONDON</hi> Printed. Anno Domini. 1593.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
